<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ evidenced to be the amen, truth it self, in the three most important significations thereof whereby the foundation of our religion, the ground of our faith, and the infallible authority of the Holy Scriptures are established : which were delivered in a sermon preached October 14th before the Right Worshipful the mayor, recorder, aldermen, and sheriff, on the morning, at St. Nicholas Church in the town and county of New-Castle, upon Tyne / by Thomas Davison ...</title>
            <author>Davison, Thomas, b. 1639 or 40.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37265</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12791161</idno>
  <idno type="VID">93943</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240971745</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4658</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12791161</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 378:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ evidenced to be the amen, truth it self, in the three most important significations thereof whereby the foundation of our religion, the ground of our faith, and the infallible authority of the Holy Scriptures are established : which were delivered in a sermon preached October 14th before the Right Worshipful the mayor, recorder, aldermen, and sheriff, on the morning, at St. Nicholas Church in the town and county of New-Castle, upon Tyne / by Thomas Davison ...</title>
                  <author>Davison, Thomas, b. 1639 or 40.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for Robert Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  History of doctrines --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93943:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93943:1"/>
            <p>CHRIST Evidenced to be the <hi>Amen, Truth it self.</hi> In the Three most Important <hi>Significations</hi> thereof: WHEREBY The Foundation of our <hi>Religion,</hi> the Ground of our <hi>Faith,</hi> and the Infallible Authority of the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> are Established.</p>
            <p>Which were Delivered in a SERMON Preached <hi>October</hi> 14th. before the Right Worshipful the <hi>Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen,</hi> and <hi>Sheriff,</hi> on the Morning, at St. <hi>Nicholas-Church,</hi> in the Town and County of <hi>New-Castle,</hi> upon <hi>Tyne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Davison,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>PRESBYTER in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> at <hi>Balmbrough</hi> in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and sometimes Student in St. <hi>John's Colledge</hi> in <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</p>
               <bibl>Plutarch. de Isid. &amp; Osi.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>St. <hi>Joh.</hi> cap. 14. v. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the sign of the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93943:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93943:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend and Right Worshipful <hi>John Sudbury,</hi> Dr. in Divinity, Dean of <hi>Durham,</hi> and one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Chaplains in <hi>Ordinary.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHat <hi>Simplicius</hi> says of some Beings, that, for the compleating the Order of the Universe, were Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, <hi>Utriusque nexus mundi:</hi> is applicable to that Place you stand in, in this famous <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> you being, <hi>utriusque vinculum Ordinis,</hi> the highest of the Inferiour, and nearest Boarder on (what nothing but an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled Modesty and Self-denyal, could have hindred your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving to, long ere this, <hi>The highest Dignity of the Clergy;</hi> You not only knowing, but Ingrossing the Perfections of both. And therefore to one that moves (though its his greatest Honour bet to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) in the lowest Orb of its Order, as my self doth, (and who is mightily influenced by such great Lights as your self) to have prefixt your Name, (without your Knowledge and Consent) to this Dedication, would have been an unpardonable Crime. But that I know your Candor is so great and generous, as to give a kindly Reception to what ever hath but the Resemblance, much more, to what bears the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the greatest Truth (as the Subject of the following Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course doth; and that that Comprehensive <hi>Charity</hi> of yours, which can cover a multitude of Sins in Persons, would not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to correct what Faults may drop or flow from my Pen; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially about a Subject, which is such a substantial Truth, that that Eloquent Father <hi>[Lact. Just. de Veritat.]</hi> calls it, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulum animae. St.</hi> John, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> That which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains such wounderful Rarities and Super-Excellencies, that it ministreth New Matter of Admiration to the blessed Angels, even in their Beatisick Contemplations and Visions of it; whose <hi>Source</hi> and <hi>Head,</hi> like that of <hi>Nilus,</hi> becomes not only Dark, but to the nearest Approaches (of any Mortals Eye) must darken; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares, <hi>1 Cor. 13.12.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That we have but cloudy Conceptions of it in this
<pb facs="tcp:93943:3"/>State, the brightest &amp; most illustrious Exhibition whereof, being reserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the other; which then we shall there behold <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in its Unvailed Face and Appearances. And therefore I am the bolder to expose to publick View, these my Twilight Apprehensions of the Eternal Ʋncreated Truth, under the shadow of those <hi>Meridian</hi> Ones of yours, most brightly displayed in the visible Representation of the <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> in that Learned and Profound <hi>SERMON,</hi> on <hi>1 Tim. 3.15.</hi> Your <hi>Pillar</hi> being most firmly built on that Rock, erected on that Basis, which Christ the <hi>Amen</hi> (in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Sermon</hi>) is described to be. And without Insinuation, <hi>Sir,</hi> to your most Advanced and Admired Parts; I humbly conceive, you have so unalterably fixt it on its proper Basis, that <hi>J. S's</hi> Foundation for sure Footing in <hi>Christianity,</hi> proves but <hi>Sandy</hi> and <hi>Sliding:</hi> your <hi>Pillar</hi> becoming like that of <hi>Hercules,</hi> a <hi>ne plus ultra,</hi> to the <hi>Romish-Church's,</hi> or to any other Local <hi>Church's Infallibility.</hi> The Ʋniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal, Catholick and Apostolick <hi>Church</hi> being only Invested with an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to Deliver, as is demonstrated, (not to make) New <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> and to declare the Ʋnshakenness and Ʋnmoveableness of what it is grounded on) Christ's the <hi>Amen's Truth</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ground and Pillar of Truth, <hi>p.</hi> 21. 22. l. 4. 5.</note> So that the Super structure and its Foundation, the Pillar and its Basis being such near and necessary <hi>Relatives</hi> to each other, that the Former cannot stand without being supported by the Latter. To whose Judgment then, could I better recommend the Survey of the <hi>Basis,</hi> than to such a Master-Builder's, who so wisely hath Built thereon, as that he needs not be ashamed of his Work. I question not your approving what is positively asserted: (<hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Pillar,</hi> p. <hi>22.</hi>) of Christ's the <hi>Amen's</hi> Spirit, being the fittest and firmest Basis for the Pillar of <hi>Truth:</hi> I only fear that the Dimensions which I have hewen and roughly cut out, may not be proportionable to it. However, how unpolisht soever they be, when 'tis considered, that they are dugg out of the hardest <hi>Rock,</hi> (<hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>10.4.</hi>) even out of what hath been consolidated from Eternity. I presume on your favourable Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of this <hi>Dedication</hi> of them, not only in respect I may renew to your great Mind, and Contemplative Soul, what's most endearing to it, the Consideration of the greatest <hi>Truth;</hi> but also, as its a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Testimony</hi> of his just Esteem of your great Parts and Piety; and of his being-with all sincerity,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>Your Worships most Humble<lb/> and most Devoted Servant<lb/>
                  <hi>Thomas Davison.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93943:3"/>
            <head>CHRIST Evidenced to be the <hi>AMEN. &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. Cap. 3. Vers. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Write these things saith the AMEN.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Penman of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Book, St. <hi>John,</hi> the <hi>Apostle, Evangelist,</hi> and <hi>Divine,</hi> brings in CHRIST the <hi>Author</hi> of them, describing himself by such se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Characters,</hi> as did most aptly agree with, or bear a significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either to the scope and design of each <hi>Epistle;</hi> or, to the State and Condition of those seven <hi>Churches</hi> (in the <hi>Lesser Asia</hi>) to whom he writes; or to what he had to lay in Charge against them. Thus when he writes to the Angel of the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Ephesus,</hi> Rev. 2.1. Christ is represented by him, <hi>that walketh in the midst of the seven Golden Candlesticks;</hi> correspondent to what he threatens, v. 5. <hi>Viz. That he would remove their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93943:4"/>Candlestick out of its place,</hi> Viz. Either their <hi>Bishop</hi> out of his <hi>See,</hi> or the <hi>Light of his Word</hi> from amongst them, because they liv'd not up to the Enlightnings thereof; as appears from <hi>vers.</hi> 4. So when he writes to the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> v. 8. He is set forth by, <hi>Him that was dead, but is alive:</hi> intimating his <hi>Ability</hi> and <hi>Readiness</hi> to bestow on such as did persevere (in the <hi>Profession</hi> of the <hi>Faith</hi>) <hi>Ʋnto Death, a Crown of Life,</hi> v. 10.</p>
            <p>In like manner, when he writes to the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus,</hi> ch. 2. v. 12. He is brought in with <hi>a sharp two-edged Sword:</hi> signifying his <hi>fighting</hi> against, and <hi>slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering</hi> down their <hi>Atheism</hi> and <hi>Idolatry;</hi> mentioned, <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15. and this, <hi>with the Sword of his WORD,</hi> called (<hi>v.</hi> 16.) the <hi>Sword of his Mouth.</hi> Again, when he writeth to the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Sardis,</hi> ch. 3. v. 1. He is resembled to him <hi>that hath the seven Spirits, and the seven Stars:</hi> implying his sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and unexpected coming to <hi>Judgment</hi> against them for their <hi>Impenitency,</hi> v. 3. <hi>I will come as a Thief in the Night upon thee.</hi> Thus when he writes to the <hi>Angel</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> v. 7. He is pointed out by him, <hi>who hath the Keys of</hi> David: Relating either to<note n="*" place="margin">Christs</note> his being the <hi>Supream Head</hi> over his <hi>Church;</hi> or, to his <hi>unquestionable Authority</hi> and <hi>Prerogative</hi> in the <hi>designation</hi> of the <hi>Preachers</hi> of his <hi>Word,</hi> or to his wonderful <hi>Power,</hi> evidencing it self in the <hi>Conversion</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> imply'd (<hi>v.</hi> 8.) <hi>I have set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee a Door open.</hi> To the same purpose (<hi>ch.</hi> 2.) when he writes to the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Thyatira,</hi> he is charactered by him, <hi>that hath Eyes like a Flame of Fire, and Feet of fine Brass,</hi> v. 18. The <hi>flaming Eyes,</hi> importing the <hi>Glorious Attribute</hi> of his <hi>Omnisciency,</hi> his <hi>All-seeing Eye,</hi> v. 23. <hi>I am he that searcheth the Reins and Hearts:</hi> and his <hi>Feet of fine Brass,</hi> alludes to that <hi>Iron Rod,</hi> (mentioned, <hi>v.</hi> 27.) with which he would <hi>correct</hi> and <hi>crush</hi> his <hi>stubborn Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93943:4"/>or else to that <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> with which he would <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Govern</hi> them. And lastly, when he writes to the <hi>Angel</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Laodicea,</hi> ch. 3. v. 14. He is signalized by being the <hi>AMEN,</hi> as in the <hi>Text,</hi> in Opposition to their <hi>Formality</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisy:</hi> and what is also worthy our Observation, our Saviour is brought, and doth appear in these <hi>Visions,</hi> commending their <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> even whil'st he's correcting them for their <hi>Vices;</hi> teaching us, that in the midst of <hi>Wrath</hi> he can shew <hi>Mercy.</hi> And further, which will give some light to the <hi>Text,</hi> and to the following <hi>Discourse,</hi> its to be observ;d, that such as are described in the subsequent <hi>Verses,</hi> were a People that did frequent the <hi>Christian Assemblies,</hi> and adhered to them, such as had a <hi>Form,</hi> but nothing of the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Godliness,</hi> such as are described by our Saviour, as had <hi>Prophesied in his Name,</hi> Mat. 7.22. Such as St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaks of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Who creep into Houses, and lead Captive silly Women, laden with sins, led away with divers Lusts. Such who had trodden under foot the Son of God,</hi> Heb. 10.29. Such were the <hi>Gnostic Christians,</hi> who, though they had high advanced Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of their <hi>Knowledge</hi> in the deep Mysteries of <hi>Religion,</hi> and did constantly keep to <hi>Christian Assemblies,</hi> yet they did not walk up to the <hi>Precepts</hi> thereof: no more did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> as will appear by the sequel of this <hi>Discourse;</hi> for the better understanding of which, and of the <hi>Text,</hi> I shall speak to four things;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shew the various signification of the word <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> What is the import or meaning of it in the <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> What the Crimes were which the <hi>AMEN</hi> brings in charge against these <hi>Laodiceans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> Why commanded to be written.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1st.</hi> It doth, <hi>rei certitudinem ac veritatem denotari,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes the Certainty and Truth of a Thing declared, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to a <hi>Mental Design,</hi> or <hi>Reservation,</hi> and is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93943:5"/>to <hi>vero, certo,</hi> truly and indeed: thus it is taken, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Verily, verily, I say unto you,</hi> Mat. 16.28. Mark 9.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> It signifies the Compleating and Fulfilling of a <hi>Thing Promised,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> useth it (2. Cor. 1.20.) <hi>In whom are all the Promises,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Yea, and AMEN.</hi> i. e. <hi>Compleat</hi> and <hi>Accomplished.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> It implys the approving of, and assenting to <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>Praises,</hi> supposed to be well known and understood, which I take to be the meaning of that of the <hi>Apostle. Else, when thou shalt bless with the Spirit, how shall he that pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesseth the Room of the</hi> Idiot, Illiterate, <hi>or</hi> Unlearned, <hi>say</hi> AMEN <hi>at thy giving of Thanks, seeing he understandeth not what thou saist?</hi> 1. Cor. 14.16. Which by the way, lays an Imputation on the <hi>Blind Devotion</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which prompts her <hi>Votaries</hi> to set and say <hi>Amen</hi> to <hi>Prayers</hi> composed and delivered in a <hi>Tongue Ʋnknown</hi> to most, whose <hi>Zeal</hi> is breathed therein: as it doth also on the <hi>Rashness</hi> of many <hi>Separatists,</hi> in their ready assenting to, nay, commending of <hi>extempory, undigested, unconceiv'd Prayers,</hi> which, 'tis scarcely possible any <hi>Hearer</hi> should un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, when (without breach of Charity) it may be presum'd, the <hi>Speaker</hi> himself is at a loss. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> It betokeneth something <hi>Promised,</hi> to be <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,</hi> as, <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> to the Will of <hi>God;</hi> which Sense it beareth: <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. <hi>v.</hi> 15. and 28. <hi>Cursed be he that</hi> Confirmeth <hi>not all the Words of the Law: and all the People shall say,</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> It signifies an <hi>ardent Desire,</hi> or <hi>hearty Wishing,</hi> that a thing may be done: so it is to be understood in the Close of the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> (Mat. 6.13.) and of each Petition contain'd therein. In this sense also 'tis taken, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. <hi>He that testifyeth these things,</hi> saith, <hi>surely
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93943:5"/>I come quickly,</hi> Amen, Amen; <hi>so come, Lord Jesus.</hi> But <hi>AMEN</hi> in these <hi>Significations,</hi> is taken only <hi>Adverbially,</hi> and only expresseth the <hi>Mode</hi> or <hi>Manner</hi> of Affirming what is declared, to be True; or approving and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming of it to be so; or, wishing and desiring that it might be True. All which reach not that <hi>Perfection</hi> and <hi>Excellency,</hi> that comprehensive <hi>Signification</hi> of it, as 'tis taken <hi>Substantively</hi> in the <hi>Text:</hi> Which brings me to the</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Second GENERAL.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>2d. General,</hi> Viz. To shew the full Import and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it in the <hi>Text;</hi> which these following words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The Faithful and True Witness, the beginning of the</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: do fully declare, they being the full rendring of the <hi>Hebrew</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as the <hi>Learned</hi> and truly <hi>Religious</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Annot. ad Locum.</note> observes, Faithful in the discharge of that great Trust committed to him, <hi>Viz. The Revelation of his Father's Will.</hi> True, as most worthy to be believ'd by many, in that he not only sealed the Truth of his <hi>Doctrine</hi> with the shedding of his <hi>Blood;</hi> (<hi>John</hi> 14.6.) but also, in that he really is what he described himself to be, <hi>Viz. Truth it self.</hi> This is the most <hi>Pregnant</hi> Signification of Christ's being the AMEN in the <hi>Text,</hi> which is expressive of a most eminent <hi>Attribute</hi> or <hi>Property</hi> common to the three ever blessed Persons in <hi>Unity:</hi> For God the Father is called by the Prophet (<hi>Isai.</hi> 65.16.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>God of Truth:</hi> God the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> the third Person, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. i. e. <hi>the Spirit of Truth:</hi> And here in the <hi>Text,</hi> Christ, the second Person is denominated the AMEN, <hi>Truth it self:</hi> which (like the Nature it expresseth) is incommunicable to any Creature: for, <hi>nullus unquam An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelorum, Prophetarum, aut Apostolorum veniebat, dicens,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> None of the <hi>Angels, Prophets,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93943:6"/>and <hi>Apostles,</hi> durst ever presume to deliver any <hi>Message</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> to <hi>Earth,</hi> with an, <hi>I, the AMEN, say unto you:</hi> as a Learned Man observes<note n="*" place="margin">See Leudov. de Dieu ad Locum.</note> For, though, when the <hi>Being</hi> of an <hi>Angel</hi> agrees to the Nature of an <hi>Angel;</hi> his <hi>Conceptions</hi> to the Truth of his <hi>Being;</hi> and his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions</hi> (or manner of declaring his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions</hi>) to the Truth of his <hi>Conceptions;</hi> he's called, <hi>True:</hi> So, though an <hi>Angel</hi> be named, <hi>Just, Holy, Good,</hi> and <hi>True</hi> in the concrete yet he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be called<note n="*" place="margin">Yet such is the wicked Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy of the Bp. of <hi>Rome,</hi> as to assume this Title to himself.</note>
                  <hi>Holiness</hi> it self, <hi>Justice</hi> it self, <hi>Goodness</hi> it self, in the <hi>Abstract:</hi> no more can he be properly named, <hi>Truth</hi> it self: for 'tis an Establisht <hi>Maxim</hi> in <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Schools,</hi> that, <hi>De ente increato, nempe Deo, solum abstracta prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantur, concreta vero de creato.</hi> For in the Nature of every Creature, how simple soever it be, we conceive a <hi>Composition,</hi> something as constituting, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answering to <hi>Form;</hi> something constituted answering to <hi>Matter,</hi> as <hi>Metaphisitians</hi> term them; which is wholly repugnant to, excluded from the Nature of GOD, and of that <hi>Conception</hi> which we form of the <hi>Simplicity, Single<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and <hi>Oneness</hi> of his <hi>Deity.</hi> So fully is the word <hi>Amen,</hi> expressive of Christ's <hi>Divinity.</hi> And as a farther Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence thereof, 'tis worth our Observation, that <hi>Amen, Amen, I say unto you,</hi> in the N. T. is equivalent to, <hi>Ego vivo, Dominus;</hi> As I live saith the Lord, in the Old; as <hi>Hieronimus</hi> observes, on <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. For the Life of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists in the Stability, Steddiness, Immutability, and in the Truth and Veracity of the <hi>Divine Essence:</hi> nay, the very word AMEN, taken materially, as made up of Letters, carries a probability highly correspondent to the <hi>Truth</hi> declared; for like the Nature which it signifies, it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93943:6"/>self, is <hi>Invariabilis,</hi> its interial constituent Letters, being <hi>Retainds</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew, Caldee, Syriac, Arabic, Greek, Latin,</hi> and in the Modern <hi>Tongues,</hi> as Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men have<note n="*" place="margin">Ludov. de dieu. Eras. Bed.</note> observ'd, intire and whole, without any change or alteration; not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist on what <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Sacredness</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded within its Significancy (being some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what Extrinsive and Forreign to that signification of it which we have now in prospect and pursuit) with which the most solemn, and most serious <hi>Performances</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> are concluded; with which their <hi>Prayers</hi> &amp; <hi>Praises</hi> breath the very life, the very lust of their <hi>Ardure</hi> and <hi>Fervency;</hi> with which their <hi>Spiritual</hi> Power and Efficacy ascends up to the Throne of <hi>Mercy,</hi> to the Throne of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> where even the Hallelujah's, Heavenly Transports, Ecstasied Joys of the Confirm'd <hi>Angels,</hi> and of the Spirits of <hi>Just Men,</hi> made <hi>Perfect,</hi> are closed withal; and that it will be the Conclusion (may I so express it) of their everlasting <hi>Hymns</hi> and <hi>Praises.</hi> So that AMEN, in its remotest signification, expresseth the Sublimest <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> the Highest <hi>Truth,</hi> Viz. the <hi>Eternal</hi> and <hi>Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Truth,</hi> Viz. God the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Original:</hi> God the <hi>Son,</hi> the <hi>Revealed;</hi> and God the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> the <hi>Proceeding Truth. Truth</hi> being the very <hi>Basis</hi> of the Divine <hi>Essence,</hi> and Attributes of the Divine <hi>Essence:</hi> for God being the <hi>Only True God,</hi> (Joh. 5.20.) is differenced and distinguished from all <hi>False Gods,</hi> such as <hi>Idols,</hi> which the <hi>Prophet</hi> calls, <hi>Teachers</hi> of <hi>Lyes,</hi> Hab. 2.18. And also, of the <hi>Divine Attributes;</hi> for, without it, God's <hi>Ʋnchangiableness</hi> would be a most fluctuating, uncertain Thing; his Almighty <hi>Power,</hi> but helpless <hi>Weakness,</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing its <hi>Strength</hi> from <hi>Imagination;</hi> His <hi>Goodness</hi> might be deemed to be but the Overflowing of a <hi>pregnant Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> and not such as springs from so <hi>Benign</hi> and <hi>Bountiful</hi> a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93943:7"/>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> as the <hi>Divine</hi> is: and his <hi>Mercy</hi> would prove but an uncomfortable <hi>Sanctuary</hi> to miserable <hi>Supplicants</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> if it were not reallized. But as AMEN signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the <hi>Eternal Truth,</hi> so it implys its being the <hi>Original</hi> of all <hi>Truths:</hi> Hence Christ, the AMEN, is called in the Close of the Text, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Beginning of the Creation, by whom all</hi> Things <hi>were made,</hi> Col. 1.15, 16. And according to his Eternal <hi>Platform</hi> of Truth, all <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> derived theirs: for though, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found late Lord <hi>Bishop</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">See his Discourse of <hi>Truth,</hi> p. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Dromore</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> maintains, and that upon weighty <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons:</hi>
                  <q>That not only the Nature of Things, but also their mutual <hi>Respects</hi> and <hi>Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> are <hi>Immutable, Ʋnchangeable,</hi> and <hi>Eternal,</hi> being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent to any Understanding <hi>Created,</hi> or <hi>Ʋncreated.</hi>
                  </q> Yet, (in <hi>pag.</hi> 27.) he grants, nay, positively affirms, <q>That Things are so far from having any <hi>Being</hi> antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to the <hi>Divine Ʋnderstanding,</hi> that had it not been their great Exemplary <hi>Pattern</hi> and <hi>Idea,</hi> they had never been <hi>Created,</hi> they had yet been undiscriminated in the Womb of <hi>Nothing.</hi>
                  </q> And consequently, that the Truth of Things being interwoven with their very <hi>Essences,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivative from <hi>Christ</hi>'s, the AMEN'S, the <hi>Original</hi> of All; but too near approaches to the Inaccessible <hi>Light</hi> of this Eternal, Uncreated Truth, proves <hi>Darling.</hi> And therefore, to prevent my self and my <hi>Reader</hi> from being puzzled in the further Researches after it, as <hi>Pilate</hi> was, when he questioned, <hi>What is Truth?</hi> Joh. 18.38. I proceed to a second and more <hi>Immediate Signification</hi> of the word AMEN, <hi>Viz.</hi> As it importeth the Truth of Christ's <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions</hi> (pardon the <hi>Expression</hi>) imply'd in the Truth of these <hi>Visions,</hi> which he revealed to St. <hi>John:</hi> for <hi>Christ</hi> (not St. <hi>John</hi>) is the <hi>Author</hi> of them, as appears by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93943:7"/>Title of this Book, (<hi>ch.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 1.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>The Revelation of Jesus Christ:</hi> who, without all peradventure, could not but clearly see, and know the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nature of Things, as they are in themselves; in that he <hi>Created</hi> and <hi>Formed</hi> them after the Model of those Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Ideas,</hi> which were irradiated by, and shone most brightly in his Divine Understanding: by which the Truth of what he hath delivered, becomes most <hi>Infallible,</hi> and most <hi>Certain.</hi> And therefore, what Person could be more eminently qualified for, and essentially endued with the Motives of <hi>Credibility,</hi> than Christ the <hi>Amen?</hi> Who fitter to reveal the Eternal Purposes of <hi>Heaven</hi> to <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> than He? Who is not only intimately and eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly present to, but doth fully and equally participate of one and the self same Nature with God the <hi>Father;</hi> whose obscurest and darkest Secrets none could know, <hi>but he to whom God, the Son, should reveal them,</hi> as Christ declares, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27. If one of the most advanced Order of the <hi>Creation,</hi> one of those Virgin and Undeflowred <hi>Beings,</hi> of the <hi>Holy Angels,</hi> whose <hi>Perfections</hi> is Knowledge and Understanding, makes the nearest approach to that which is <hi>Incomprehensible</hi> in God; and whose <hi>Will</hi> was never perverted by any Wickedness, being now Confirmed in <hi>Goodness,</hi> and in <hi>Glory:</hi> and therefore might not be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, or suspected to have (in what he should reveal) any design to Impose on the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Belief</hi> of Man: yet his <hi>Revelation</hi> could not pass for Infallible Evidence, nor his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, He hath said it, for uncontroulable <hi>Authority;</hi> for he would fail in point of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and so would be deficient in one main motive of <hi>Credibility.</hi> On which account, I conceive, St. <hi>Paul</hi> (Gal. 1.8.) doth not only reject, but <hi>Anathematize,</hi> declare <hi>Accursed</hi> the <hi>Revelation</hi> of an <hi>Angel,</hi> when it's repugnant (which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93943:8"/>would argue very strange <hi>Darkness</hi> and <hi>Weakness</hi> of his Understanding) to what Christ, the <hi>Amen,</hi> hath taught and delivered as <hi>Sound</hi> and <hi>Saving.</hi> Can we think then, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have embraced for <hi>Blessed,</hi> those Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilential <hi>Doctrines,</hi> breathed as <hi>Salutary</hi> and <hi>Healthful,</hi> by <hi>Oral Tradition;</hi> when he would reject such, though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by an Angel? But though we cannot imagine such Wickedness in a Holy Angel, as to delude us with False <hi>Doctrines;</hi> yet we cannot be Infallibly certain of what he delivers, to be True; for though he doth, <hi>uno in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitu,</hi> at first view, know the very Nature of Things; yet, as to <hi>Futurities, Contingencies,</hi> and of what is to come, he's at a loss. The Angels were ignorant (as our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> declares, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.36.) of his coming to <hi>Judgment</hi> against the <hi>Jews:</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> also asserts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 12. That they did not know the Errand of Christ's <hi>Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> of the end of his <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and of his <hi>Churches;</hi> and after these, of his <hi>Ascention</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi> So defective would an Angel be, in point of Knowledge. But again, what an Angel may know of Things to come, is but by a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed Light from the <hi>Father</hi> of Light, by <hi>Revelation;</hi> so that his Testimonies would not be believed, or received as Angelical, but as Divine; for the ultimate Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Faith and Belief, must be unto Divine Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. How pitiful, as well as proud, then must the vain Pretences of the <hi>Bishop,</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> be, who would obtrude on the <hi>Christian World</hi> his <hi>Private Dictates</hi> for <hi>Infallible Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Postquam se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel Romae consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum est, veri, rectique Normaem in Causam Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis esse, non verbum Dei, non antiquitatis consensum, sed Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae, <hi>i. e.</hi> unius Papae infallibilitatem. <hi>Is Casaub. exerc. 16.</hi> pag. <hi>443. l. 31, 32.</hi>
                  </note> Whereas the best that ever was in that <hi>See</hi>'s Perfections, falls migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93943:8"/>short of those of an <hi>Angel,</hi> both in point of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and of <hi>Purity;</hi> and both theirs, and these of an Angel, infinitely below Christ's, the AMEN'S Infallibility, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Veracity, in what he reveals to St. <hi>John:</hi> for it was not possible that these <hi>Visions</hi> should be meer <hi>Illusions,</hi> or <hi>Deceptions:</hi> for Christ did not only infallibly know the present State and Condition of these seven <hi>Churches</hi> in the lesser <hi>Asia;</hi> but also did foresee what False <hi>Teachers, Formal Worshippers</hi> of him, would arise in his Church, (branched into particular <hi>Churches</hi>) throughout the World; nothing could escape the Inspection of his All-seeing Eye: so that his Testimony could not fail in point of <hi>Knowledge:</hi> and it was as impossible it could be defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as to <hi>Integrity;</hi> that he should impose on St. <hi>John</hi> with Delusions &amp; Falsities, such being diametrically and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opposite to what he is in the <hi>Text,</hi> and this by his own Command described to be, <hi>Viz.</hi> the AMEN, TRUTH it self. So that the Word of <hi>Truth</hi> becoming visible, hath brought within our Prospect and View, the Eternal and Uncreated <hi>Truth,</hi> exhibits as present to, what was so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant from us, as God's Eternal Purposes and Designs, as to our <hi>Salvation,</hi> were. Thus in time we are brought ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the greatest Mysteries of <hi>Eternity,</hi> and now we may read with our Eyes the most endearing Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters (O ineffable, unspeakable Condiscention!) of Gods <hi>Eternal Love</hi> to Mankind. But yet the Glories of the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, Ʋncreated Truth,</hi> and of this Revealing it self to St. <hi>John,</hi> might at this day, been wrapt up in <hi>Darkness</hi> and <hi>Obscurity,</hi> been yet the hidden Mysteries of <hi>Eternity.</hi> If the Intellectual Faculties of St. <hi>John,</hi> and Man's, had not also <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Veracity</hi> stampt on them, communicated to them by <hi>Christ,</hi> the AMEN: Which is the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93943:9"/>
                  <hi>Third,</hi> and <hi>Last</hi> Thing imply'd in it: For Christ being (as God) not only the chiefest <hi>Good,</hi> but the chiefest (as is signified by his being the AMEN) <hi>Truth:</hi> for which the self Originated, or First Being becomes more fitly qualifyed to be the Fountain from whence doth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Foundation, on which is built the Truth and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity of Man's <hi>Faculties,</hi> as it is most ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally asserted by a late<note n="*" place="margin">See Des Cartes Princ. <hi>p. 2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Philosopher.</hi> And we find one enlightned with a better and a clearer <hi>Ray;</hi> I mean, St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Evangelist,</hi> grounding the Infallible Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of what was Revealed to him, and the unquesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable Credibility of what he wrote, of what he deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Christians,</hi> on the Truth of his <hi>Faculties: That which we have heard, which we have seen with our Eyes, which we have handled, of the Word of Life, that declare we unto you,</hi> 1 John 1.3. Nay, he expresly declares, That <hi>the end for which Christ hath given to us Ʋnderstandings,</hi> is,<hi>That we may know him that is True,</hi> 1 John 5.20. Otherwise these <hi>Visions</hi> might have appeared to St. <hi>John,</hi> as delud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Dreams; Truth</hi> it self, as disguised <hi>Falsity;</hi> and so neither He, nor We could be certain of any Thing, but <hi>Ʋncertainty.</hi> But since the Foundations of the Earth shall sooner fail, and the Immense <hi>Rafters</hi> of Heaven snap in sunder; since the very Heaven shall run together like a <hi>Scroll,</hi> and the Element be dissolved by most fervent Heat, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> most lively represents (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.) the Conflagration of the World, before the coming of the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Terrible Day</hi> of the Lord: And since a greater than he (<hi>Viz.</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi>) hath plainly and positively declared, (in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18.) <hi>That both Heaven and Earth shall pass away, before one</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Jot,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93943:9"/>
                  <hi>Tittle, or</hi> Point (as some read<note n="*" place="margin">Who encline to that Opinion of Hebrew Points, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in use in our Saviours Days, I am sure it points out the Infallible Authority of the Scriptures, as <hi>Scriptae.</hi>
                  </note> it) <hi>of the Law shall pass, till all be Fulfilled.</hi> And as a farther Confirmation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that he will be with his <hi>Church</hi> (not by his Bodily Presence, for that is in Heaven; nor by his Essential Presence, for <hi>Fiends, Devils,</hi> and the wickedest of <hi>Men</hi> are not excluded from it; but) by his most gracious Presence, to guide and direct her by his <hi>Word,</hi> and by his <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> in the Knowledge of all <hi>Truth</hi> (neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to be known for the obtaining Everlasting Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness) We have the AMEN's (<hi>Truth</hi> it self) Promise for it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Lo, I will be with you always, even unto the End of the World,</hi> Amen. Thus the Foundation of God, and of our Salvation, standeth sure; the Ground of <hi>Faith</hi> (Christ the AMEN being the Chief <hi>Corner-Stone</hi> thereof) remains Unshaken, and the Infallible Authority of what he commanded (as he did these <hi>Visions,</hi> and also the other <hi>Revelations</hi> contained in the <hi>Bible</hi>) to be written, are most clearly illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated (not to say,<note place="margin">Casaub. Exerc. <hi>16. p. 672. col. 2.</hi> St. Aug. de Civit. <hi>lib. 10. cap. 16.</hi> ubi expressis ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ostendit vir sanctissimus, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi e Scripturis, nec miracula fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienti, potius credendum esse; quam miracula facienti, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Scripturam loquenti nihil enim credere Deus voluit, adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Scripturarum Auctoritatem.</note> Demonstrated) by three most important significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, deduced from the word AMEN; as it is taken <hi>Substantively</hi> in the <hi>Text.</hi> But since we ought to listen to Truth at all times, yet most chiefly we are to lend to it a more attentive Ear, when it speaks from Heaven, and is so parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93943:10"/>concerned to correct the Errours, and to reform the Manners of the Inhabitants of the Earth, as doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Christ the AMEN was, by what he brings in charge against the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which leads me to the</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Third GENERAL.</head>
               <p>To shew what Christ saith against her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1st.</hi> He chargeth these <hi>Laodiceans</hi> with unconcerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> with Indifferency in both, that like <hi>Lukewarmness</hi> in water, they did partake of neither of the Extreams, <hi>Heat</hi> nor <hi>Cold,</hi> being neither downright <hi>Atheists,</hi> nor upright <hi>Christians;</hi> whereas Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion &amp; Devotion should have been of the greatest <hi>weight</hi> and moment with them, should have sunk most deeply into their Hearts and Affections; with which they should have been most sincerely affected, as with what could best suit their Profession, as <hi>Christians;</hi> set forth God's Glory as <hi>Worshippers;</hi> and would be most subservient to the Salvation of their Souls, as <hi>Believers:</hi> but instead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as if they were both things at the greatest Levity and Lightness, nothing but empty, airy <hi>Notions,</hi> they fluctuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and floated in the heads of these <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended into their Hearts, that they might be form'd there, by the Grace of God, into a Spiritual Love: which so highly reflected on the Truth which they professed; and on Christ the AMEN, or Author of it; that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour passionately wisheth they had been <hi>Cold; I wish thou wert Cold.</hi> Which we are not to understand, as if Christ had desir'd, that they had been such desperate wicked <hi>Sinners,</hi> as never received any Inward Heat or Warmth from his Holy Spirit: but his meaning is, It had been better for them, if they had never known, or heard of any such Being, as the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> or <hi>Spirit;</hi> in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93943:10"/>that <hi>Sins</hi> of Ignorance are not so gross and grievious as those are, that are committed against Knowledge, as these Scriptures declare, <hi>Viz. The Servant which did know his Master's Will, and did it not, was to be beaten with more stripes than he that was ignorant of it,</hi> Luk. 12.47. And, <hi>It had been better not to have known the ways of Righteousness, than after they have known it, to turn from the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment delivered to them,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.20. For Sins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted against Knowledge, imply the Perverseness of the Will against Light; which, those committed through Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, evidenceth the want of it: for which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly meet with a more favourable Reception at the Hands of Mercy, than the others do: yet so fond are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as to flatter themselves with a Self-Sufficiency, as to their Eternal Safety, even whil'st they are gratifying their <hi>Sensuality,</hi> under the Disguise, the Paint and Varnish (as many of these <hi>Laodicians</hi> did, <hi>pag.</hi> 17.) of <hi>Hypocrisy. Because thou saist, thou art rich, encreased in Goods, and stands in need of nothing,</hi> &amp;c. Which though it be the vainest Garb, the most Formal Dress of <hi>Christians;</hi> yet, rather than want one, (these <hi>Laodiceans</hi>) were resolved to wear it. Which is the</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second</hi> Thing to be considered, <hi>Viz.</hi> Their <hi>Hypocrisy.</hi> Which is a most hainous and destructive Sin, for it cheats the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> of his own Soul, whil'st he imposeth on, and deceiveth others, and attempts to do the like to God, for which 'tis deservedly called, a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Iniquity:<note n="*" place="margin">Simulata San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitas est duplex Iniquitas.</note> for the Formal <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipper</hi> doth not only think, that God doth not see, but (what is no less than <hi>Blasphemy</hi>) that God doth approve of his <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi>) as the <hi>Psalmist</hi> declares, <hi>Psal.</hi> 5.29. — <hi>Thou thoughtest that I was altogether such an one as thy self.</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93943:11"/>Otherwise he durst not (as many of the Church of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea</hi> did) bring his Body to Church, to Religious As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, and leave his Soul cumbred (like <hi>Martha</hi>) about the Concerns of his Home; and suffer his Soul in time of Worship (like its Tempter) to wander to and fro on the Earth, when it should be fixed on what is Heavenly. So that whil'st he deceiveth <hi>Man</hi> Out wardly, he highly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoureth God Inwardly; and indeed, the Thoughts which a <hi>Hypocrite</hi> hath of God, are not only <hi>Superstitious</hi> and <hi>Mean,</hi> but most <hi>Contemptible</hi> Ones, even whil'st his <hi>Sacrifices</hi> are most Pompous and Splendid, Rich and Cost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; whil'st like the <hi>Athenians</hi> and other <hi>Grecians,</hi> he Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bulls with gilded Horns<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Plato, Alc.</hi> 2d. p. 254.</note> or Offereth up ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand <hi>Rams,</hi> poureth out ten thousand Rivers of <hi>Oyl;</hi> nay, spareth not what should be dearest to him (as the Prophet elegantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribes the Height of <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> Mic. 6.6.) his <hi>First-Born;</hi> for he vainly thinks that God is profited, and much better<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by these his magnificent and stately <hi>Sacrifices:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as one, no great Favourer of a <hi>Deity,</hi> Viz. <hi>Lucretius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lucret. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Natura.</note> entertains more generous and noblier Thoughts of his Nature; which he thus declarer — <hi>Ipsa suis pollens opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nil indiga nostra.</hi> And one endued with a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd Light, <hi>Eliphaz,</hi> the <hi>Temanite</hi>'s Question, puts it out of all doubt; <hi>Can a Man be profitable unto God, as a wise Man man may be unto himself?</hi> Job. 22. <hi>v.</hi> 2. Or, what Gain is the <hi>Hypocrite</hi>'s seeming Righteousness unto the Almighty? For he is not only an All-sufficient, but a Self-sufficient Being. And tho God requires Prayers and Praises from his Creatures, as <hi>Homages</hi> of their Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency on, and of their Obedience to him; yet he gains
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93943:11"/>nothing by both or either; but the Glory of his Grace shining in the Goodness of the Creatures Performance of the one, and thankful Acknowledgment of the other; but the Heinousness, and Destructiveness of these <hi>Laodiceans</hi> Hypocrisy, will further appear, if</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> We consider their Spiritual <hi>Pride,</hi> a common Companion of <hi>Hypocrisy;</hi> which like <hi>Leaven</hi> did not only four their <hi>Performances,</hi> and so rendered them disgusted; but also puft them up (with what rendered them disdain'd) with inward <hi>Pride,</hi> and a vain Confidence of a self-Sufficiency, as to their Eternal <hi>Welfare</hi> and <hi>Safety:</hi> for these <hi>Laodiceans</hi> thought they were rich enough in Grace, that they stood not in need of Christ's Gifts, nor of the Garment of his Righteousness, v. 17. meerly because they did constantly frequent the <hi>Christian Assemblies:</hi> whereas the <hi>AMEN</hi> did not only know, but plainly tells them, that they were <hi>poor, wretched, miserable, blind,</hi> and <hi>naked,</hi> v. 17. But <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> had rendered their Condition sensless, and the means of their Conversion ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry difficult, if not altogether useless: for being not sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Sickness of their Souls; they made no Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their Spiritual <hi>Physitian,</hi> to <hi>Christ</hi> their Saviour. In which Sense I understand that Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.12. <hi>They that be whole need not a Physitian.</hi> Such a sound, and whole Person was the Formal <hi>Pharisee,</hi> whom our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our describes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.11. by his Prayer. In which wee find no Confession of Sin, no Supplication for Pardon, no Importunity for Increase of <hi>Faith,</hi> no <hi>Zeal</hi> for Enflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Love, no Earnestness for daily <hi>Aids,</hi> and <hi>Assistan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> from Gods <hi>Holy Spirit:</hi> But on the other hand, a vain Confidence in his own Righteousness, a Boasting of (with <hi>I thank thee, O Lord</hi>) and a Glorying in, what he should have been mightily humbled under; <hi>viz.</hi> God's Restraining Grace, in that he was <hi>not like,</hi> for lewd, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93943:12"/>notorious Sins, to the Poor <hi>Publican;</hi> who for all that was dismissed from the Footstool of Mercy, and absolved Penitent; whereas the Proud <hi>Pharisee</hi> goes out of the <hi>Temple</hi> unconcernedly, though hardened in his <hi>Hypocrisy.</hi> But not to insist, that the worst of Torments (which shews its most baneful to Souls being reserved for it) in the other state, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.5. <hi>Appoint his Portion with the Hypocrites.</hi> It's a Sin most destructive to them in this: for <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> staves Souls off from a <hi>Cordial</hi> embracing the Tenders of Mercy. This is the sin, these are the Crimes, which <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>AMEN</hi> laid in Charge against the Church of <hi>Laodicea.</hi> But that we may not think that these sins were confin'd only to the bounds of <hi>Asia,</hi> and to the time, when these <hi>Visions</hi> were revealed; and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality</hi> was only the peculiar sin of the <hi>Laodiceans;</hi> but that many Thousands in after and succeeding Ages would arise, and be found as Formal <hi>Worshippers</hi> of God, and Christ; as well as these <hi>Laodiceans</hi> were. For the Prevention therefore of the <hi>Growth</hi> of <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> and for the Increase of Love to <hi>Truth</hi> in the inward Parts amongst <hi>Christians</hi> in the Ages to come, is one (but not the only) Reason, why Christ the <hi>AMEN</hi> commanded St. <hi>John</hi> to consign these Visions to writing, which brings me to the</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Fourth</hi> and <hi>Last</hi> GENERAL.</head>
               <p>Why commanded to be written. To ascertain to us the Infallible Authority of the Holy Scriptures, as <hi>Scriptae;</hi> for I cannot conceive, that what is <hi>Infallible</hi> in it self, (as these <hi>Visions</hi> were) when delivered by Christ to St. <hi>John,</hi> should be lessened in its Authority, when commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to writing any more than what is delivered by word of mouth, as these <hi>Visions</hi> were at first. Not only because Christ commanded them to be written; which he would never have done, if the so doing should have lessened ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93943:12"/>the <hi>Credibility,</hi> or <hi>Infallibility</hi> of them; and also <hi>Litera scripta manet;</hi> but also, because words fluctuate, float in the Air; and so the Essentials of a <hi>Doctrine</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by them) may be soon dispers'd, and lost: So that there is very little, if any Safety at all, for sure-foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Christianity</hi> on <hi>Oral Tradition:</hi> I am sure, and am confirmed in it by very good hands; that many dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and destructive <hi>Doctrines,</hi> both to <hi>Religion</hi> in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and to <hi>Christianity</hi> in Particular, have sprung from <hi>Oral Tradition.</hi> The <hi>Worshipping</hi> of the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> called <hi>Zabaism;</hi> and the <hi>Adoration</hi> of many Gods called <hi>Hellinism,</hi> or <hi>Polytheism</hi> had their Rise, and Original of some broken <hi>Traditions</hi> conveyed from the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">See Bochart. Phaleg. Gules. Gentil. Court. <hi>1.</hi> T. C. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>105.</hi>
                  </note> And as for the <hi>Doctrines</hi> destructive to <hi>Christianity</hi> in Particular: Such as these that destroy the Satisfaction of <hi>Christ</hi> and a <hi>good Life;</hi> as the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Merits doth the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping</hi> but of one God: which the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Worshipping</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> doth destroy. The Having but one <hi>Mediator,</hi> and <hi>Intercessor</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares) betwixt God and Man; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. which is multiplied into Thousands by Praying to Saints and Angels. The <hi>Adoration</hi> of the Creator, is given to the Creatures by <hi>Worshipping</hi> of the <hi>Host.</hi> The Evidence of sense destroyed by the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Transubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> and the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of <hi>Holy Writ;</hi> by that of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Tradition;</hi> from whence all these dangerous, and damning Doctrines did at first flow; and are at present zealously (though but blindly) embraced by most; and stifly defended by some in the Church of <hi>ROME.</hi> By such <hi>Tradit ons</hi> the <hi>Commands</hi> of God and <hi>Christ</hi> are <hi>made,</hi> or become (to too too many alas!) of <hi>none Effect:</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:93943:13"/>but, if, to invalidate the Authority of the Scriptures, what St. <hi>Peter</hi> saith (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.) be Objected, and which the Unlearned and Unstable wrest to their own Destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Reply is ready, <hi>Viz.</hi> That it is not any Unsound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Doctrines contained therein, but the Injudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and wicked <hi>Minds</hi> of those that pervert them, which doth destroy: for as wholesome Food taken into a <hi>Foul Stomack,</hi> corrupts there, &amp; so becomes <hi>Destructive</hi> to what otherwise it would have been <hi>Preservative</hi> of (the Health of the Body) Or, as from the vain <hi>Imaginations</hi> which Men have had of the One only <hi>True God,</hi> hath sprung a Plurality of <hi>Deities,</hi> and laid the Foundation of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> than which nothing could be more repugnant to the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and <hi>Design</hi> of that God, who upon no account will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; nay, hath expressly forbidden, <hi>That his Honour and Worship should be given to another.</hi> So the main Tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the <hi>Doctrines</hi> delivered in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> is to build us up in a most Holy <hi>Faith;</hi> which the <hi>wresting</hi> of them doth pervert, to the destroying the End thereof, <hi>Viz. The Salvation of our Souls:</hi> whereas many <hi>Doctrines</hi> (such as are above named) delivered by <hi>Oral Tradition,</hi> carry along with them in their most <hi>genuine</hi> and <hi>natural Sense</hi> or <hi>Motive,</hi> what is of a good Life, destructive of a found Faith; and so hazards the <hi>Damning</hi> of those, who readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embrace (and without the least hesitancy or doubt) do firmly believe them. But we have a surer <hi>Word of Prophesy, even the written Word of God, which is able to make us wise unto Salvation,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19. Also, <hi>throughly to furnish us with all good Works,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.17. Out of a deep sense of which it was, that most famous <hi>General Council</hi> held at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> had such a Veneration for the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that it erected a magnificent <hi>Throne</hi> above the <hi>Seats</hi> of the <hi>Council,</hi> on which they placed the <hi>Holy Bible;</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93943:13"/>alledging its Authority above theirs, tho a <hi>General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> as <hi>Justellus</hi> reports the <hi>Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of that <hi>Council:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Passim haec verba reperiuntur, <hi>Viz.</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Interposita in medio Sacro-sancta &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerablia Evangelia. Item, H <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>i. e.</hi> Sanctus Synodus Christum constituit consessorem, ac ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut Caput: deinde Evangelium in Throno sacro collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum Sacer dotibus insonans, Justum Judicium Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. <hi>Just. in Can.</hi> Page <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> Agreeable to which, also is that of St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in his <hi>Apolegetic</hi> to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius</hi> the Emperour, <hi>Viz.</hi> Speaking of the <hi>Council</hi> at <hi>Ephesus</hi> in this manner, The <hi>Holy Synod</hi> doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Assessor</hi> and <hi>Head,</hi> and place the Venerable <hi>Bible</hi> on a sacred Throne, crying out, or aloud, (as it were) to the <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> then present, <hi>Judge me Just, Ʋpright Judgment;</hi> which may cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the <hi>Insolent Arrogancy</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who assumes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self the proud Title of being, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Ʋniversal,</hi> but <hi>Infallible Head of the Church;</hi> which all the <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bishops</hi> and <hi>Priests,</hi> assembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in these <hi>Councils,</hi> durst not as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume; but most humbly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Christ to be the <hi>Ʋniversal Head</hi> over his Church, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be her <hi>Infallible Guide.</hi> In which sense a late <hi>Critick</hi> [<hi>See Heins Exerc. sacrus.</hi> p. 147.] inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prets that of St. <hi>Luke c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Now when he had ended all his Sayings. Quasi</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i. e. Of the Self sufficiency of the Divinely inspired <hi>Scriptures:</hi> which is one main end why Christ the <hi>AMEN</hi> commanded these Visions to be written. But,</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93943:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Which more particularly did concern these <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans,</hi> Viz. To perpetuate to Posterity God's and Christ's Detestation of <hi>Hypocrisy:</hi> a sin so hateful to God, that it made him out of love with those very Times and Places, (though of his own Institution) which otherwise used to be the delight of his Spirit, <hi>Viz.</hi> His <hi>Sabbaths</hi> and <hi>Sanctuarys</hi> under the <hi>Law:</hi> the <hi>Altar</hi> did hallow the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice;</hi> and the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> Religious Actions done thereon: But <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> desecrated the one, and unhallowed the other. Hence God is brought in by the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> 1.13. Complaining of the <hi>New-Moons</hi> and <hi>Sabbaths;</hi> nay, declaring himself <hi>wearied</hi> with (what otherwise would have rejoyced him) their <hi>solemn Meetings.</hi> And no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it should be thus, that God should so abominate the very <hi>Sacrifices</hi> of the <hi>Hypocrites</hi> (or disguised <hi>Wicked Ones</hi>) for <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> is mightily provoking of (what God is most averse to) <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Fury:</hi> in that it most grosly abuseth and contemneth God's <hi>Omnisciency,</hi> Psal. 10.13. For <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> doth with God, as the <hi>Philistines</hi> did with <hi>Sampson,</hi> puts out his All-seeing Eyes, and then sports it self, as they did, in abusing of it: which (as the <hi>Psalmist</hi> declares, <hi>Psal.</hi> 73.11.) <hi>How doth God know?</hi> And with a <hi>Tush</hi> (Psal. 94.7.) <hi>God doth not see; neither doth the God of Jacob regard</hi> (what he cannot behold without Abhorrency) <hi>its hidden and secret Iniquity.</hi> But as its a sin abominated of God, so 'tis also disgustful to Christ; it had rendred the Religious Performances of these <hi>Laodice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> so <hi>Crude</hi> and <hi>Raw,</hi> that they could not down with <hi>Christ;</hi> and when they did, it was but to cast them up in such a manner as declar'd, his <hi>loathing</hi> and <hi>abhorring</hi> of them; imply'd by his <hi>spewing them out his mouth.</hi> By which he would teach <hi>Christians</hi> in <hi>After-Ages,</hi> to shun and fly <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> as <hi>Moses</hi> did from before his Rod, when it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93943:14"/>with the face of a <hi>Serpent:</hi> otherwise, too near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to, and frequent use of it, may sting them to Death: and also, that its <hi>Righteousness</hi> is but like the Weavings of a <hi>Spiders Webb,</hi> which transmits the sin, and what it causeth, shame; both which it should cover, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth both to the Inspection of the <hi>All-seeing Eye:</hi> and that its <hi>Remains</hi> will prove as deadly as <hi>Poyson;</hi> for the Artificial Colours of <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> are like the Paintings of <hi>Jezabel,</hi> but specious Indications of a Whorish <hi>Heart,</hi> gadding after <hi>strange Gods;</hi> or, what is not <hi>God.</hi> And therefore, that its end, like hers (since God and Christ do so justly abhor it) will prove <hi>Wretched</hi> and <hi>Miserable,</hi> 2 King. 9.33. This is another Reason why these <hi>Visions</hi> were commanded to be written. But,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> To perpetuate Christ's Care and Watchfulness over his <hi>Church:</hi> for he the <hi>Bidegroom</hi> being gone before, to prepare for his <hi>Bride, Mansions</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> Joh. 14.2. Least, by his so long stay or absence from her, as till the End of the World, least he should seem either to leave her Comfortless (which that he would not do, she hath both by <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Writing</hi> from him for it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.18.) or kindle her <hi>Jealousie,</hi> that he was forgetful of her; or to prevent her being <hi>Fond</hi> of other Lovers, he caused <hi>stamp</hi> (as it were) on Paper, the <hi>Indelible Characters</hi> of his Heart and Affection towards her; that though she could not hear his Voice, which is most Ravishing; nor see his Face, which is altogether comely: yet she might read in these his Epistles of <hi>Love,</hi> what might transport and ravish her, <hi>Viz.</hi> His constant Care and Vigilancy over her, teaching her not to make her Addresses, or to put up her Petitions with <hi>Courtship</hi> and <hi>Complement,</hi> with Formal Shews and Pretences: but in such a manner as became the Gravity and Chastity of his <hi>Beloved,</hi> Viz. with Truth and Sincerity. Which is the</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:93943:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourth</hi> and <hi>Last</hi> Thing to be insisted on, and Reason why Christ the <hi>Amen</hi> commanded St. <hi>John</hi> to write these <hi>Visions,</hi> Viz. To teach those <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> and all <hi>Christians</hi> in succeeding Generations, to worship God with Inward Sincerity, which is best agreeable to the Nature of God, as he is a <hi>Spirit;</hi> and to that of the <hi>Amen,</hi> as he is <hi>Truth it self:</hi> and to what he hath enjoyned, <hi>John</hi> 4.24. Viz. <hi>They that Worship God, must worship him in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> For without <hi>Inward Truth</hi> and <hi>Sincerity,</hi> our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship will be but like a <hi>Body</hi> without a <hi>Soul,</hi> cold and dead, appear but with the shape of what it wants, its Enliven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Form. For though these <hi>Laodiceans</hi> might appear with fresh and fair Faces in the <hi>Religious Assemblies;</hi> yet they had but cold and dead Hearts; however, not so much <hi>Inward Heat,</hi> as could denominate them <hi>Living Worshippers</hi> of the <hi>True God:</hi> else Christ the <hi>Amen</hi> had not so affectionately (as he did) wisht, they had been either <hi>Cold,</hi> or <hi>Hot,</hi> v. 15. And therefore, by way of <hi>Corallary,</hi> I shall conclude with the <hi>Amen's</hi> Exhortation, <hi>v.</hi> 19. which I hope the Consideration of, ye my Readers, having read the <hi>Truth</hi> declared, as it is in <hi>Jesus,</hi> may inforce upon you. For alas! it may be presumed, without <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> that there are too too many amongst us, as well as there were in the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> who are neither <hi>Cold</hi> nor <hi>Hot;</hi> nay, who are <hi>Cold</hi> as well as <hi>Lukewarm.</hi> Let us therefore follow <hi>Christ's</hi> Exhortation, <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>Be truly Zealous, and Repent.</hi> Repent of our <hi>Coldness</hi> and <hi>Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmness,</hi> of our open <hi>Prophanen<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ss</hi> and <hi>Formal Hypocrisy,</hi> of our sporting with <hi>Sin,</hi> and of our abusing of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> if we would prevent our being plunged into Eternal Misery. For it is not our being born and brought up within the best Constituted Church (as our Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Church of England</hi> is) in the <hi>Christian World;</hi> it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93943:15"/>is not the soundness of her <hi>Doctrines,</hi> being the same which Christ the <hi>Amen</hi> taught these <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> nor the Purity and Innocency of her <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> nor the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiveness, Antientness, and Apostolicalness of her Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by <hi>Bishops</hi> (who in this and the forgoing Chapter, are honoured with the Titles of <hi>Angels</hi>) nor our frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Churches, and formal joyning with her Prayers and Praises, that can prevent our <hi>Lukewarmness</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency</hi> in the way of her Worship (as these <hi>Laodice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were in theirs) from being our everlasting Ruine, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less we speedily repent us of our <hi>Hypocrisy;</hi> make Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Christ the <hi>Amen</hi> for <hi>Eye-salve,</hi> to clear the Sights of our <hi>Ʋnderstandings:</hi> so that we may not only see the Necessity, but also the Excellency of Worshipping God with Sincerity, unless we importune for the Garment of his <hi>Righteousness</hi> to cover our Nakedness; and covet ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly for the Gold of his <hi>Grace,</hi> to enrich and adorn us; that what <hi>Formality</hi> hath rendred <hi>Mean,</hi> nay, <hi>Contemptible,</hi> the Modes of our Worship may be approv'd of as truly valuable, by the <hi>Amen, Truth it self:</hi> which will be best evidenced by our being truly <hi>Zealous</hi> for the Glory of his <hi>Grace;</hi> which by humbling us for our <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> designs to exalt us: and indeed the holy Ardour of the Religious, breathing themselves out in Zeal, is highly commended by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Gal. 4.18. <hi>It is good to be Zealously affected to every good Work.</hi> For it wipes off (from a People) that Reproach of <hi>Coldness,</hi> and <hi>Lukewarmness</hi> which the <hi>Amen</hi> reflects and casts on these <hi>Laodiceans.</hi> But then our <hi>Zeal</hi> must not be like that of <hi>Jehu</hi>'s, which had more of Light to amaze the Understanding, than of Heat to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the Affections of others: but like to that of St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist</hi>'s, which was a Burning and Shining Light, Refining the <hi>Soul</hi> from the Dross of Sin, whil'st it guides and conducts others in the ways of <hi>Sanctity:</hi> and now,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93943:16"/>if ever our <hi>Zeal</hi> ought eminently to appear in the evil Days of <hi>Schism</hi> and <hi>Separation,</hi> not only as an Evidence of that Holy Religion which we profess; for which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Object of the Hatred and Envy of all Dividing Persons from us) but also that the Sincerity of our <hi>Zeal</hi> may outvye its <hi>Paint</hi> and <hi>Varnish, Formality</hi> and <hi>Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy</hi> drawn to the Life, even in the Pretenders to, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolizers of <hi>Saintship</hi> and <hi>Holiness.</hi> By so doing, we shall vindicate the Honour of our Religion from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies of evil Men, procure to our most gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, the Defender of it, Blessings <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> and so secure a lasting Establishment of the Mode of our Worship to us, and to our <hi>Posterity.</hi> Then need we not fear that the Gates of <hi>Hell, Rome,</hi> or <hi>Geneva,</hi> shall ever so prevail over us, as to overthrow that <hi>Truth</hi> which Christ the <hi>Amen</hi> hath Established amongst us. So blessed and happy a thing it is, to be sincere zealous Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the God of <hi>Truth,</hi> to be thus guided and directed in the ways of Holiness, in the Practice of Piety, by the Spirit of Truth; for such shall be gloriously, and that everlastingly rewarded (reaping the Fruits of their <hi>Zeal,</hi> and Laborious End of their <hi>Faith,</hi> the Salvation of their <hi>Souls</hi>) by Christ the <hi>Amen, Truth it self,</hi> who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20.) to confer on such as persevere in the Practice and Profession of true <hi>Piety,</hi> a <hi>Crown of Life.</hi> Which that my Readers and my self may be made Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of, God in his Infinite Goodness, plant not only <hi>Truth</hi> in our Inward Parts, but also sincere Love and Affection to it; that we may live to the Glory of God the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Original;</hi> of God the <hi>Son,</hi> the <hi>Revealed;</hi> and of God the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> the <hi>Proceeding Truth,</hi> both now and for ever, AMEN.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:93943:16"/>
            <head>An Account of some of the Matters Treated of in the <hi>First</hi> and <hi>Second Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume</hi> of <hi>A Collection of Letters for Improvement of Husbandry and Trade,</hi> by <hi>John Houghton,</hi> Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society;</hi> to be sold by <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, and several other Booksellers.</head>
            <p>IN VOL. I. Enquiries concerning <hi>Agriculture.</hi> Advantages we might receive by <hi>Inclosure, Clover</hi> and <hi>Cole-seed.</hi> The <hi>London</hi> way to Cure <hi>Neats Tongues.</hi> Considerations about <hi>Trade.</hi> The <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Ʋse</hi> of <hi>Money.</hi> Advantage by <hi>French Furzes.</hi> An Account of Mr. <hi>Firmin's</hi> Book to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake <hi>Linnen.</hi> Dr. <hi>Plot's</hi> Letter, proposing Remedies against <hi>Uncertainty</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>Loss</hi> of <hi>Crops, Smuts, Meldews, Lodgings</hi> of <hi>Corn,</hi> and its being eaten up by <hi>Birds.</hi> An Essay, to shew that the <hi>Plantations</hi> Increase or Improve our <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople. The Manner of Planting <hi>Licorice.</hi> Best for <hi>England</hi> to have <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd, Rich. Spain</hi> not hurt by its <hi>Plantations,</hi> nor <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Prodigality,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut Enrich't by <hi>High Living.</hi> The Way and Method of Improving Land <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Marle;</hi> from Mr. <hi>Adam Martindale.</hi> The History of <hi>Malting</hi> at <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> A <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Irish Act.</hi> The way to gain the <hi>Linnen-Manufact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> The ways to make several sorts of <hi>French Bread,</hi> from <hi>John Evelyn,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sq; An <hi>Improvement</hi> by <hi>Parsly,</hi> from Mr. <hi>John Worlidge.</hi> Observations on <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>East-India Company</hi> and <hi>Bankers.</hi> A Particular of the Goods Import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to, and Exported from <hi>London,</hi> in <hi>January</hi> and <hi>February,</hi> 1682/3; with <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Number of <hi>Ships.</hi> An <hi>Experiment</hi> from Mr. <hi>Worlidge,</hi> for <hi>Improving</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Fyning Syder:</hi> with several other Things: and an <hi>Index</hi> to this First <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olume;</hi> Containing 24 Sheets.</p>
            <p>In <hi>VOL.</hi> II. A <hi>Token</hi> for <hi>Ship Boys,</hi> or <hi>Plain-Sailing,</hi> made more <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ain;</hi> from Mr. <hi>Adam Martindale.</hi> An Account of a new Manner of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lowing,</hi> whereby was done in three Days by one <hi>Man</hi> and two <hi>Bullocks,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much Work as could be done with four Stout <hi>Horses</hi> and two <hi>Men</hi> in <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght Days. A Second <hi>Experiment</hi> from Mr. <hi>Worlidge</hi> about <hi>Syder.</hi> Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ments about <hi>Port-Sea Salt.</hi> An Essay to prove it <hi>England's</hi> Interest, to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>stroy their <hi>Wood</hi> within twelve Miles of a <hi>Navigable River.</hi> The <hi>Plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g</hi> of <hi>Saffron,</hi> by the Honourable <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> Esq; <hi>Enquiries</hi> relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g to <hi>Husbandry</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi> Drawn up by the Learned Dr. <hi>Robert Plot,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. D. Keeper of the <hi>Ashmolean Musaeum,</hi> and Professor of <hi>Chymistry</hi> in <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Ʋniversity</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and <hi>Secretary</hi> of the <hi>Royal Society</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> A <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ceipt</hi> of <hi>Brunswich-Mum;</hi> and way to Improve <hi>Mossie-Land.</hi> An Offer <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> make it appear, That it is the <hi>Interest</hi> of the <hi>Subjects</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch for the <hi>Improvement</hi> of <hi>Husbandy</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi> plentifully to Supply <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir <hi>King:</hi> In a Letter to <hi>Roger L'Estrange,</hi> Esq; In all, fourty two Sheets <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> twenty <hi>Numbers:</hi> and is designed to be carried on by two, or more <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eets at a time, Monthly, or sooner, or later, as Occasion offers. And if <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y have any <hi>Proposal</hi> or <hi>Experiment,</hi> for the Good of the Kingdom, that <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey are willing to Communicate, if they please, they may send it to the <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> thereof, in St. <hi>Bartholomew-Lane,</hi> behind the <hi>Royal-Exchange, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93943:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93943:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>